Guide to the Gustave Gimon Collection of French Political Economy: general ephemera, 1669-1880
Department of Special Collections
Gustave Gimon Collection of French Political Economy: general ephemera,
1669-1880
Special Collections M0910
Gimon, Gustave
1 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Purchased, 1996.
Historical Note
The collection is named in memory of the philanthropist who also was a leader of the French Resistance during World War II. This collection of ephemera is part of a larger collection including some 1,500 books and 75 manuscripts, cataloged separately.
Scope and Content
Includes broadsides, small pamphlets, etc. pertaining primarily to legal ordinances and insurance contracts.
Access Terms
Social history.; France--Politics and government.; France--Economic conditions.; France--Social life and customs.; Gustave Gimon Collection of French Political Economy.; Gimon, Gustave.
Container List
- Legal Ordinances
  - Ordonnance ... pour le maintien de la police, de l'ordre & de la tranquillité [sic] publique --Epernay Paris, chez P.G. Simon, 22 p. 9/2/1782 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - défenses... de faire l'exercice d'aucune Confrairie,... de Maîtres, Compagnons, Apprentifs & Ouvriers Paris, chez P.G. Simon, 4 p. 11/12/1778 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Calfats de Marseille Paris, de l'Imprimerie royale. 6 p. 4/20/1786 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Maîtres et garçons perruquiers de Limoges Limoges, de l'Imprimerie de Pierre Chapoulaud. in-folio-plano. 7/28/1787 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Ordonnance Concernant les Garçons Boulangers Paris, de l'Imprimerie de J.R. Lollin. 4 p. le 23 ventose an XI 3/14/1803 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ordonnance Concernant les Garçons Boulangers Paris, Lollin de S.-Germain. 3 p. 4/23/1819, About the policing of "garçons boulangers" and the application of laws about their work papers. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ordonnance concernant les ouvriers Paris, Lottin de S.-Germain. 6 p. 6/18/1822, Ordinance serving as severe reminder that coalitions of workers are illegal. Work had stopped in several carpenters' workshops with the goal of procuring higher salaries. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Réglement pour les Maîtres & les Ouvriers Paris, P.G. Simon. 4 p. 9/12/1781, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - ... concernant les Maîtres de forges et leurs Ouvriers Paris, de l'Imprimerie royale 8/4/1786, notes written on back of ordinance. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Réglement pour les Maîtres et les Ouvriers Aix, Joseph David. 4 p. 9/12/1781 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Réglement en faveur des Ouvriers & Artisans du Fauxbourg Saint-Antoine de Paris Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 7 p. 12/19/1776 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - une Ordonnance... concernant les Compagnons & Ouvriers - Nemours Paris, chez N.H. Nyon. 4 p. 2/11/1788, Prohibiting all workers from forming associations, from assembling, and from making any conventions between themselves. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - concernant les Maîtres de forges & leurs Ouvriers Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale 8/4/1786 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Traiteurs-Restaurateurs Paris, chez P.G.Simon. 7 p. 6/28/1786, Regulations allowing traiteurs-restauranteurs to receive clients in their rooms, and giving them to eat and to drink until 11:00 in winter, and midnight in summer, and this, under the condition that they don't provide food except in their rooms. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - ... contestations entre les Ouvriers de la Manufacture des Cristaux & Emaux de la Reine - Sèvres Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale. 3 p. 12/16/1785 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ordonnance de M. l'Intendant, qui fait défenses aux Travailleurs du Lieu de Couiza... de s'opposer à ce qu'on emploie des Travailleurs étrangers... Montpellier. 2 p. 9/7/1785, Prohibiting workers from protesting against the hire of foreign workers for the construction of a bridge of Couiza. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Le Prix des journées à payer par les Maîtres Maçons, Bourgeois & Propriétaires, aux Tailleurs et Scieurs de pierres,... Paris, P.G. Simon & N.H.Nyon. 2 p. 7/26/1785 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Le maintien du bon ordre parmi les Ouvriers, Garçons & Compagnons .... de ladite ville de Moulins Paris, chez P.G. Simon & N.H. Nyon. 8 p. 2/21/1785, Ordinance concerned with the maintenance of order among various classes of workers who are employed by merchants and artisans in the town of Moulins. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Défenses à tous ouvriers de retenir où de vendre les pennes, bouts, corons, etc. Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale. 4 p. 3/14/1784, Prohibiting workers from stealing supplies and products from their employers and then selling them. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Ordonnance du Siège de la Police de la Ville de Tours, concernant les Ouvriers, Garçons & Compagnons Paris, chez P.G. Simon & N.H. Nyons. 7 p. 9/5/1783, Ordinance composed of 7 articles, followed by a model of a work certificate to be filled out by the "maître" for the "garçon" when the latter has finished his contract. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Concernant le temps d'Apprentissage dans les Communautés du ressort du Parlement de Paris Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale. 2 p. 11/24/1782, Fixes length of apprenticeship at 4 years. fleur de lys watermark. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ordonnance... de Nogent-sur-Seine, pour l'ordre & la tranquillité publique Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 31 p. 6/26/1782, Long ordinance (76 articles) about maintaining public order and tranquility. Some articles concern the policing of work and workers. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Règlement pour les Maîtres & les Ouvriers dans les Manufactures & dans les Villes... Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale. 4 p. 9/12/1781, 9 articles and model of a work certificate to be filled out by employer for the worker. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Qui défend les attroupemens & émeutes des Ouvriers employés à la Moisson dans l'étendue du Bailliage de Laon... Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 4 p. 8/7/1780, Authorizes officers of justice to carry out all necessary ordinances for the payment of workers (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "les difficultés entre les ouvriers employés à la moisson... les fermiers & cultivateurs des terres,... pour raison du prix de la moisson des grains" Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 3 p. 8/3/1780, On the difficulties between workers employed for the harvest in the parishes of Gonesse, Aulnay, and surrounding areas and the farmers and cultivators, over the price of the grain harvest. Because it is important to maintain public order and tranquility. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Qui défend les associations & attroupemens des Compagnons des différens Arts & Métiers Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 4 p. 11/12/1778, Prohibits associations made up of compangons from different arts and professions. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ordonnance de police, concernant les domestiques Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 4 p. 11/6/1778, Ordinance composed of 7 articles, extremely severe, on domestic servants who in spite of their inferiority, belong to a society where luxury becomes more widespread as the coutryside becomes depopulated. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Réglement en faveur des Ouvriers & Artisans du Fauxbourg Saint-Antoine de Paris Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 7 p. 12/19/1776, Declaration facilitating the admission of workers and artisans to be masters in the Community of Arts and Crafts of Paris (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ordonnance de Police, concernant les Garçons Cordonniers Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 4 p. 9/2/1777, 17 articles about working conditions, hiring and firing of "garçons cordonniers" (shoemakers) of Paris. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Concernant les Serruriers, Taillandiers, Ouvriers travaillant à la Forge, Ferrailleurs, Revendeurs & Crieurs de vieilles ferrailles Paris, L.F. Delatour. 4 p. 7/10/1776, Strict ordinance primarily concerned with the fabrication of keys and locks. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Extrait des Registres du Parlement Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 4 p. 6/28/1775, Prohibiting compagnons and apprentices from carrying sticks or arms, day or night. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Arrest de la Cour de Parlement... défenses aux Maîtres de Manufactures... de donner du travail à aucuns Ouvriers... Rouen, chez Jean-B. Besogne. 6 p. 7/21/1749, Ordinance prohibiting rural manufacturers in the region of Rouen from hiring workers during the harvest, and mandating that persons needing to glean the fields have a certificate of neediness and infirmity so that they are not arrested for laziness. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ordonnance du Bureau de Police d'Aix portant reglement provisionnel pour les Travailleurs, Lavandieres, Maçons... Printed poster. in-folio plano. 5/8/1724, Prohibiting workers to demand higher wages for their work day than those fixed by this ordonnance, "etant juste que le paysan en cultivant gange le pain qu'il est oblige de manger," despite the fact that the value of the "denree" has fallen. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Arrest de la cour du Parlement de Toulouse... portant reglement pour les journées des travailleurs des vignes & des terres Toulouse. Poster in-folio plano. [1718], Poster announcing that workers of the land cannot leave their homes until the ordinary works of the season have been done; with the fine of 25 livres. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Reglement fait par M.M. du Parlement et Magistrats de la Chambre de la ville de Dijon pour les compagnons menuisiers... Manuscript in fine handwriting. 2 p. half in-folio. 7/24/1693, Regarding compagnon woodworkers who must conform to the rules of this ordinance and previous ordinances under threat of corporal punishment. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Declaration du Roy, Portant défenses aux gens de Mer & de Métier de la R.P.R. d'aller s'établir dans les Pais Etrangers Lyon, chez Antoine Jullieron..., avec privilège de sa Majesté. 4 p. 6/3/1682, Prohibiting all people of the sea and of the trades and their families from leaving the kingdom. Cites religion as one of corrupting factors outside of France. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Arrest du Conseil D'Estat du Roy... les personnes qui exercent l'Art & Mestier de Cousturière n.p. 4 p. 5/31/1675, Regards the taxes that the clothesmakers must pay, and the penalties for not paying them. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Arts et metiers, Maitrise de Rotisseur Patent. Printed and Manuscript. Parchment. in-folio oblong. 3/10/1730, Patent of Masters in Rotisseur granted to Louis Riquet, Paris region, town of Mantes. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Arrest de la Cour des Monnoyes, qui interdit Claude-Francois Gauché Maitre Orfèvre à Paris... Paris, au Palais, chez Claude Girard. 8 p. 8/6/1740, Arrest and legal memoire regarding the punishments given to Gauche for having protected the compagnon Jean Giboux. Documents the legal case brought by the king's Procureur General (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Reglement... concernant les Ouvriers des Departemens & Quartiers des Classes de la Marine... Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale. 3 p. 1/6/1722, Regarding the Intendants of the Marine receiving a count of workers engaged in marine trades. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Observations... contre la communauté des maîtres chirurgiens de la même ville [Lyon]... d'avoir fait le métier qu'on appelle communément Charlatan Lyon, chez C.A. Faucheux. 4 p. 7/2/1774, Charging Jean-Pierre Devoluy and his wife, Clemence Richard, of having circumvented the laws of medicine and surgery, "that is to say, of having practiced the trade that is commonly called CHARLATAN." (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Arrest du Conseil d'Estat, portant que les Maistres, Compagnons, Ouvriers, ... de la ville de Lyon... Lyon, de l'Imprimerie d'Antoine Valancol. 7 p. 8/5/1669, Regarding the relations between the different levels of workers and the merchants of Lyon, including explanations of diverse privileges. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Ordonnance du Bureau des Finances de la Généralité de Paris, concernant la police dans les Ateliers de Paveurs, & la conservation des Ouvrages publics Paris, de l'Imprimerie Royale 8/2/1774, Regulations regarding the roadbuilders and pavers of Paris. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Arrest de la Cour des Monnoies, qui fait défenses aux Maîtres Orfèvres de protéger les Ouvriers sans qualité Paris, chez P.G. Simon. 3 p. 5/22/1773 [s.d.], Prohibiting Master silversmiths from protecting unqualified workers (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Jugement de la Sénéchaussée-Criminelle de Lyon. Qui fait défenses à tous Compagnons-Serruriers, de s'attrouper & de s'assembler en quelque endroit. Lyon, de l'Imprimerie de P. Valfray. 3 p. 9/24/1767, Regulating the right to assembly of Compagnons-Serruriers (locksmiths), "pour raison de la cabale & conduite seditieuse." (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reglement Statuts et Ordonances des Maistres du Metier de Pannetier, Vannier,... de ceste ville et Banlieue de Rouen... Registered in Parlement. Manuscript on vellum. 13 p. in quarto. 2/18/1669, The text of this statute is not included in Ouin-Lacroix's work Les Corporations de la ville de Rouen. Probably only extant copy. Collector's note says that it is finely dated 6 April 1720. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Le Chapelier Loi Relative aux Assemblés d'Ouvriers & Artisans de même état et profession - "La Loi Le Chapelier" Paris, L'Imprimerie royale 1791, Very important law banning the right of workers of the same trade to form associations (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Calonne Ordonnance de M. de Calonne... qui fait défenses à tous Ouvriers attachés aux manufactures ..., de sortir des Provinces... sans être munis d'un passe-port Lille, de l'Imprimerie de N. J. B. Peterinck-Crame 1783, Ordinance prohibiting workers attached to a business to leave the provinces of Flandres and Artois without a passport. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Pamphlet
  - Callery, Alphonse Les Reformateurs de l'Ancienne France, la precurseur de Law: La Jonchère (1718-1720) Fontainebleau: E. Bourges 1880, Brief summary of the works of La Jonchere, one of the principle economic reformers of the Old Regime. Excerpt from "La France Judiciere" "Tire a trente exemplaires non mis dans le commerce," signed "a M. de Boitiste, Hommage de l'auteur" (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Publications
  - Mémoire sur l'apprentissage et sur l'éducation industrielle, ... par M. César Fichet. Paris, Imprimerie de Galban, rue de Paris,10, a Belleville. 36 p. 1847, In this pamphlet, Fichet, a teacher and founder of an "Ecole d'arts et metiers, proposes to address the inconveniences of apprenticeship by creating true professional schools. Neither the author nor his brochure are cited in the Dictionnaire de pedagogie. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Les Caisses d'Epargnes,..." par M. Cormenin. Douzième publication du Populaire. Paris, Imprimerie de Herhan. 8 p. [1834], The author of this pamphlet, Louis de Cormenin was neither a neo-babeuviste nor a socialist. He was one of the leaders of the the struggle against the government of Louis-Philippe. This pamphlet was published by Cabet's Populaire. It discusses the utility of popular savings banks and the necessity of founding more of these institutions both in Paris and in the departements in the interest of the proletariat. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Cabet, Etienne "Moyen d'améliorer l'état deplorable des ouvriers" - Septième publication du Populaire [Paris] Imprimerie de L. -E. Herhan 1833, Pamphlet contains a discussion between a sick worker, a tailor, a jewelry maker, and a republican doctor. This was the seventh publication of the Populaire, a neo-babeuvist journal published by Cabet between 1833-35. It was sold on the street at the same time as the journal. (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Insurance Ephemera
  - Compagnie d'Assurances Generales Compagnie d'Assurances Générales. Police. Contre l'incendie. Conditions Générales. part printed, part manuscript. 4 p. 12/4/1825, Insurance document. Printed general conditions of the company's insurance policy followed by handwritten specific policy of M. B. Richard, insuring his goods against fire for the sum of 5000 francs, for a period of 7 years. Signed by Richard as well as by the insurance agent. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Taylor, A.S. and Tardieu, Ambroise Etude Médico-Légale sur les Assurances sur la Vie Paris: J.-B. Bailliere et fils. Published work, 121 p. 1866, Excerpt from Annales d'Hygiene Publique et de Medecine Legale. Regards the legal matters of life insurance. Includes table of contents. Includes listing of other titles carried by the bookseller, and listing of other titles by M. Tardieu. Cover off. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - un paysan Lettres d'un paysan sur les Assurances Agricoles... par le Journal Le Messager de la Bourse. Paris: Aux Bureaux du Messager. 45 p. 1857, Small paper bound book of thoughts about the government's system of agricultural insurance, supposedly sent to the journal for presentation to the Conseils Generaux. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Societe d'Assurances Reciproques... Societé d'Assurances Reciproques, pour les Recoltes en Grains et Vins, contre les Ravages de la Grêle. Toulouse: de l'Imprimerie de Benichet frères. 19 p. Germinal, an X, Small paper pamphlet, pages uncut. Contains founding articles of the company. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Boyer, G.S., Pensionnaire de l'Etat Projet d'Assurance Générale de Bienfaisance Nationale et de Secours Mutuel dans les 86 Departemens;... La Ferte-Sous-Jouarre: Imprimerie de Guedon. 23 p. 1842, Small paper bound pamphlet. Cited in Kress, S. 6790. Describes a plan of general insurance for all members, both male and female, of the working classes. Addressed to mayors, subprefects, prefects, economists, "societes de savants," the press and the government. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Compagnie d'Assurances Générales sur la Vie Taux de la prime annuelle d'une Assurance de 100 fr., effectuée pour 1 an, 5 ans, 10 ans, où pour la vie entière. n.p. [Compagnie d'Assurances Générales sur la Vie] n.d., 1 sheet, printed on recto verso with tables of insurance rates. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Compagnie Royale d'Assurances sur la Vie Compagnie Royale d'Assurances sur la Vie n.p. [Compagnie Royale d'Assurances sur la Vie] 1835, 1 sheet, printed recto- verso with tables of different rates of insurance. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - de Courcy, Alfred Les Assurances sur la Vie en Angleterre et en France Paris, Librarie Economique de Guillaumin et Cie. Published pamphlet, 32 p. 1863, Excerpt of work entitled "Essai sur les Lois du Hasard" Imperial stamp on t.p. About life insurance in England and in France. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Borie, Victor Le Patrimoine Universelle Paris, Armand Anger, Libraire-Editeur. Published pamphlet, 24 p. 1874, With introduction by Michel Chevalier, ex-St-Simonien, "Membre de l'Institut et Professeur au College de France" 10th edition. About life insurance in France. Back cover: advertisement for "Le Moniteur des Assurances, revue mensuelle" (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Barrau, Pierre-Bernard Projet d'assurances reciproques pour les maisons, contre l'incendie Toulouse, de l'Imprimerie de Benichet Freres. 51 p. Germinal, an XI, Barrau was "Directeur de la Societé d'assurances etablie à Toulouse, pour les recherches contre la grêle, membre de la Societé libre des Sciences, Lettres, et Arts de Paris." Pages uncut. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - La Societé d'assurances reciproques contre la Grêle Assurances Contre la Grêle Toulouse, La Societé d'assurances reciproques contre la Grêle. 28 p. 1806, Document contains: "Rapport" by M. Barrau and "Comte Rendu... pour ce que concerne la Caisse des Graines " with tables containing names and insurance figures. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Petition contre le monopole des assurances par l'Etat addressée a l'Assemblée Nationale Paris, Imprimerie de E.-B. Delanchy. 23 p. in-quarto. 1848, Explanation of insurance system. Includes names of government and private insurance companies. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Petition. Manuscript. 12 p. post- 1788, "A Son Excellence, Monseigneur le Comte Angl[?], Ministre Secretaire d'Etat, Prefet de Police du Departement de la Seine" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - divers Compte Rendu le 28 juillet 1821 a l'Assemblée Générale des Actionnaires de la Compagnie d'Assurances Générales... n.p. 31 p. 1821, "Sur les opérations des trois societés pour les assurances Contre les risques maritimes, contre l'incendie, et sur la vie des hommes" Different reports by the directors of three insurance companies. Addressed on cover to M. [...] Roux (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Compagnie Royale d'Assurances, divers Compte Rendu le 27 fevrier 1821 a l'Assemblée Générale des Actionnaires de la Compagnie d'Assurances Générales... Paris, Imprimerie de P. Dupont,, Hotel des Fermes. 20 p. 1821, "Des opérations des deux societés pour les assurances: Contre les risques maritimes et contre l'incendie" Different reports and statistics by the president and censeurs of the insurance companies. Addressed on cover to M. Desgrand (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - [De Sartine] Entreprise des Voitures pour les Incendies. Second avis au public. [Paris], Chez P.F. Gueffier 1765, Statement of purpose of an enterprise proposing to bring prompt help to fires in the city of Paris. The enterprise also proposes to supply water, which has been taken from the Seine and purified by a hydraulic machine, to the public. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - [De Sartine] Avis important [Paris], Chez Gueffier. 16 p. 1767, Describes the organization of the services for putting out fires in the city of Paris. (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Reboul, Eugene Qui s'assure s'enrichit Paris, Armand Anger, Libraire-Editeur. 9th ed. 8 p. 1874, The importance of life insurance. Back cover: advertisement for "Le Moniteur des Assurances, revue mensuelle" (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Compagnie d'Assurance des Crédits Commerciaux Statuts presentes l'approbation du gouvernement Marseille, Typ. et Lith. Barlatier-Feissat et Demonchy. 22 p. 1855, Articles of the Compagnie d'Assurance des Crédits Commerciaux, "Siège de la Societé: Marseille" (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - la Compagnie d'Assurances Générales, divers Compte Rendu le 4 fevrier 1832, a l'Assemblée Générale des Actionnaires de la Compagnie d'Assurances Générales... Paris, Imprimerie de P. Dupont et G. Laguionie. 32 p. 1832, "Sur les Operations des trois Societés pour les Assurances [:] Contre les Risques Maritimes, l'Incendie Et sur la Vie des Hommes" Reports by the directors and censeurs of the insurance companies. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Signed "Hèvre" Demande d'Organisation d'une Administration centrale, à Paris, d'Assurances Speciales contre l'Incendie pour tout le Royaume Paris, Imprimerie de A. Bobée. 13 p. post 1825 (n.d.), Proposes the creation of a central firefighting association for the entire kingdom. Copy 1 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Signed "Hèvre" Demande d'Organisation d'une Administration centrale, à Paris, d'Assurances Speciales contre l'Incendie pour tout le Royaume Paris, Imprimerie de A. Bobée. 13 p. post 1825 (n.d.), Proposes the creation of a central firefighting association for the entire kingdom.Copy 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - divers Statuts de la Compagnie d'Assurance avec Reciprocité, Contre l'Incendie, la Grêle, et l'Epizootie Auch, de l'Imprimerie de Mme. Ve. Duprat. 15 p. 1819, Articles and statistics of the insurance company. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Societé d'Assurances Mutuelles sur la Vie des Hommes Une Heure Chez Mon Notiare Paris: C. Ballard. 36 p. 1823, Description of benefits of having insurance (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie Compte Rendu le 29 Mars 1866, a l'Assemblée Générale, des Operations de la Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie. 16 p. 1865, Annual report for 1865 for the insurance company "La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie, anciennement Compagnie Royale" (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie Compte Rendu le 30 Mars 1868, a l'Assemblée Générale, des Operations de la Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie. 16 p. 1867, Annual report for 1867 for the insurance company "La Nationale, Compagnie d'Assurances sur la Vie, anciennement Compagnie Royale" (Box 3, Folder 27)